Listen to a talk on a history podcast.
In the 19th century, cities in the United States became crowded.
Many businesses and apartments were housed in tall buildings.
Fires became a major concern.
Most firetruck ladders only reached the fourth floor,
which wasn't high enough.
Although laws were passed to require escape routes, many early ideas were impractical, like
one idea was to attach a parachute to your head.
The parachute idea, well, this wouldn't work too well, would it?
Other such ideas were met with resistance, too.
Enter Anna Connolly,
who received patents for fire escapes in the 19th century.
Anna Connolly's initial fire escape design was a bridge so people could safely go up to the roof
or upper floors of their own building, cross to the building next door,
and go down the stairs there.
This made good sense since most fires started on the lower floors of buildings.
After this design, Connolly created another that was a series of platforms attached to
the side of a building with ladders connecting them.
She specified they'd be made of iron, since iron is fireproof and resists pressure.
Well, this design worked, was practical,
and was adopted across the country.
Connolly's fire escapes saved lives.
These days, buildings in the US are built with interior stairwells that are fireproof for escape
and are not visible from the outside.
But you can still see Connolly's design on older buildings in cities.